<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.2">
<info>
<title>Invisible XML</title>
<author>
<personname><firstname>Norm</firstname><surname>Tovey-Walsh</surname></personname>
</author>
<pubdate>2022-02-21</pubdate>
<copyright><year>2022</year><holder>Norm Tovey-Walsh</holder></copyright>
<abstract>
<para>This article is a draft that I intend to submit to
XML.com for publication. Please don’t share this URI at this time.
Thanks.</para>
</abstract>
</info>

<para>Invisible XML is a language for describing the implicit
structure of data, and a set of technologies for making that structure
explicit as XML markup. It allows you to write a declarative
description of the format of some text and then leverage that format
to represent the text as structured information. That sounds a bit
abstract, so let’s start with an example:</para>

<para>Suppose you have a document, <filename>contacts.txt</filename>,
where you keep the names, email addresses, and other details of
friends and colleagues. It might look something like this:</para>

<programlisting linenumbering="unnumbered"><![CDATA[John Doe
john@example.com
555-1234

Mary Smith
m.smith@estaff.example.com
+1-222-555-2344

Jane Doe
(512) 555-9999

Nancy Jones
nancy@example.org]]></programlisting>

<para>This is obviously a toy example, but it will work to illustrate
a few points. First of all, those of us who are used to working with
marked up data (such as XML or JSON) are likely to think of this as
“unstructured” data. But that’s not really true. There is structure
there, it’s just indicated with whitespace and other informal
conventions, rather than with angle brackets or curly braces.</para>

<para>The real world is full of data marked up using different
conventions. We use files like this every day: email headers, ical and vcard
files, CSS, Java property files, Windows “ini” configuration files,
BibTeX, Markdown, etc. At finer levels of granularity, we find even
more examples: ISO 8601 dates and times, XPath expressions, CSS
selectors, and so on. And then we have our own ad hoc formats in
countless text files: diaries, todo lists, calendars, event planners,
etc. There are probably a dozen or so files like this within easy
reach wherever you’re reading this.
</para>

<para>This is fine when the important consumers are human readers
looking at the text. But what happens when we want to use that data in
some other system? What happens when we want to extract the
information out of these documents structured by conventions of
spacing and punctuation?</para>

<para>A common approach would be to write a script to read the format:</para>

<programlisting language="python"><![CDATA[#!/usr/bin/env python3

contacts = []
with open('contacts.txt', 'r') as infile:
    contact_id = 0
    expect_name = True
    for line in infile.readlines():
        line = line.strip()
        print(contact_id, line)
        if line == "":
            contact_id += 1
            expect_name = True
        elif expect_name:
            contacts.append({ "name": line })
            expect_name = False
        elif "@" in line:
            contacts[contact_id]["email"] = line
        else:
            contacts[contact_id]["phone"] = line]]></programlisting>

<para>That’s horrible, and not just because it’s a bit of sloppy code
I banged out in a few short minutes. (Way more of the world’s
infrastructure relies on code someone put together for a prototype or
a demo than you’d care to think about.)
The real problem here is that this tells you nothing about the
file format beyond what you can glean from the source code. These
kinds of procedural or imperative definitions of a file format, even
if they’re backed up by some sort of prose description (that you hope
is up-to-date with the latest version of the code, even though you
know it isn’t), are difficult to understand, difficult to
test, and difficult to reason about.</para>

<para>Can I put an address in this file? Is it ok if I have two blank
lines? If I have a phone number but not an email address, can I just put
in a blank line for the email address? For anything bigger than a toy
example, these are not easy questions to answer.</para>

<para>You would be much better off if you had a declarative
description of the format. Declarative descriptions are more accessible,
easier to reuse, and generally require less coding.</para>

<para>So why, you might ask, don’t we use them all the time?
</para>

<para>We do. Your XML processor, your JavaScript engine, your JSON
tooling, the compilers that built your web browser and your operating
system, are all driven by parsers that take declarative descriptions
of a system plus some input, construct an abstract representation of
that system, and operate on it. Under the hood, our favourite software
is making constant use of declarative descriptions.
</para>

<para>Okay, but why don’t <emphasis>we</emphasis> use them all the
time?</para>

<para>There are a couple of reasons. Historically, it was expensive. I
mean computationally expensive. But
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%27s_law">Moore’s Law</link>
has pretty much sorted that out. The other reason, the real reason, is
because it’s <emphasis>hard work</emphasis>. Off-the-shelf tools are
mostly designed to build incredibly efficient parsers that can analyze
huge amounts of data, unambiguously and efficiently, with only a
character or two of lookahead. Writing format descriptions for those
tools is a specialized skill that few of us have.</para>

<para>But it doesn’t actually have to be hard. Or at least, nowhere
near <emphasis>that</emphasis> hard. What makes it a specialized skill, and what makes it
hard, is fitting your declarative description into those very tight
requirements: no ambiguity and no (or only a small, fixed amount of)
lookahead.</para>

<para>Luckily, that’s not the only way to approach the problem.
Techniques for parsing that are tolerant of ambiguity and prepared to
engage in (more-or-less) arbitrary lookahead have been around for
decades. They are not as fast, or as memory efficient, as traditional
parsers, but they can be competitive in many cases. And we have
Moore’s Law on our side! Those problems are no longer significant in
many environments.</para>

<para>Invisible XML provides a specific syntax for declarative
description that’s easy to use and easy to understand. Combined with
a parser that understands Invisible XML, you can apply those descriptions
to your data and get structured data out. No (imperative) coding required.</para>

<para>Before we dig in deeper, let’s establish a little bit of
vocabulary. An Invisible XML document is a
<glossterm>grammar</glossterm>. As a term of art in computer programming,
a <firstterm>grammar</firstterm> is essentially a
set of rules. Each rule describes a <glossterm>symbol</glossterm> in
terms of some other symbols.</para>

<para>If you’ve ever used regular expressions, you’re familiar with
these ideas, even if you didn’t use this exact vocabulary. If you’re
matching data in Python or XPath, or any language with regular
expressions, and you say that an integer is a string that matches
<code>[-+]?[0-9]+</code>, you’ve created a grammar rule:
<code>integer: [-+]?[0-9]+</code>.</para>

<para>Invisible XML collects these rules together.
Each rule has a “left hand side” and a “right hand side”. The left hand
side is a single symbol, the one being defined, and the right hand side
is a list of one or more symbols that define it.
A <firstterm>symbol</firstterm> is either the name of something,
in which case there must be a further rule that defines it, one that has it as the
rule’s left hand side; or it’s something that literally matches
characters in your input.
With these rules, the processor will work out whether it’s possible
to match the whole input string that you gave it by applying these
rules in some order.</para>

<para>Let’s take a very small example. Suppose we want to match
sentences of three letter words like “see cat sat”. We could write
an Invisible XML grammar like this:</para>

<programlisting>sentence  : word+" " .
word      : consonant, vowel, consonant;
            consonant, vowel, vowel.
vowel     : ["aeiouy"] .
consonant : ["bcdfghjklmnpqrstvwxyz"] .</programlisting>

<para>We’ll come back to the specific details about syntax and how to
write an Invisible XML grammar in the next article, for now we’ll just
do a little hand waving.</para>

<para>That grammar has four rules and you can read them like this:
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>sentence</emphasis> is one or more occurrences of
<emphasis>word</emphasis> separated by a single space.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>word</emphasis> is a <emphasis>consonant</emphasis>,
followed by a <emphasis>vowel</emphasis>, followed by a
<emphasis>consonant</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">or</emphasis> a
<emphasis>consonant</emphasis> followed by two consecutive
<emphasis>vowel</emphasis>s.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>vowel</emphasis> is literally “a”, “e”, “i”, “o”, “u”,
or “y”.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>consonant</emphasis> is literally any one of the
other lowercase, English language letters, and also “y”.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Note that there’s nothing procedural here. There’s no attempt to
say how you do anything with a word or any of its constituent parts.
The grammar just declaratively describes the format. It’s easy to answer questions
about this format. Are numbers allowed? Can words be more or less than
three letters long? Is punctuation allowed? No, no, and no, respectively.
And it’s easy to imagine writing tests to ensure that this grammar does
match what you want.
</para>

<para>Of course, there is software that’s going to process it. The
first thing a processor, or parser, is going to do is determine whether the
input you gave it matches the grammar (you’ll sometimes see this
written as “checking if the input is a sentence in the grammar”).
In order to do that, it has to know where to start, so you need to nominate
one of the symbols as the “start symbol”. In Invisible XML, that’s the
symbol in your first rule, so “sentence” in this case.
</para>

<para>We can imagine a parser, given this grammar and the one word
sentence “cat”, doing something like this:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Does the input match <emphasis>sentence</emphasis>? I don’t know,
what’s a sentence?
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A sentence is one or more <emphasis>word</emphasis>s separated
by spaces. Does the input match <emphasis>word</emphasis>? I don’t know,
what’s a word?
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A word is either:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>consonant</emphasis>, followed by <emphasis>vowel</emphasis>,
followed by a <emphasis>consonant</emphasis>, or 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>a <emphasis>consonant</emphasis>, followed by a <emphasis>vowel</emphasis>,
followed by another <emphasis>vowel</emphasis>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Does the input match that? I don’t know, what’s a consonant?
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>consonant</emphasis> is one of a set of letters. Ok. Does
the first letter match one of those? Yes, “c” is one of those letters.
Great. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Does the rest of the input match the rest of the “right hand side”?
The next thing is <emphasis>vowel</emphasis>. Does the rest of the input
match that? I don’t know, what’s a vowel?
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>vowel</emphasis> is one of a set of letters. Ok. Does
the next letter match one of those? Yes, “a” is one of those letters.
Great. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>And on it goes, matching symbols against rules until it runs out
of symbols or runs out of input. In this case, it will run out of
input after it matches the “t”.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>There’s no input left. If we stop here, are we finished with the
right hand side of the rule for the start symbol? Yes? Great. Yes,
“cat” is a <emphasis>sentence</emphasis>.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>As you can see, the parser uses the rules to replace symbols
with what those symbols can be in a kind of recursive process that
“bottoms out” when it reaches something that has to match the input.
Sometimes you’ll see the class of symbols that can be replaced by
other symbols identified as “<firstterm>nonterminals</firstterm>” as
distinct from the symbols that literally match against the input, the
“<firstterm>terminals</firstterm>”.</para>

<para>What happens if it doesn’t match? What happens, for example, if
we give this grammar the input “frog”? In that case, the parser will
tell you it couldn’t match your grammar (“the input is not a sentence
in the grammar”). Something like this:</para>

<para>Parse failed. At position 2, found unexpected “r”.
Would have permitted: ["aeiouy"].</para>

<para>So your grammar also functions as a validator for your input!</para>

<para>On a successful parse, the other thing an Invisible XML parser has to do is tell
you <emphasis>how</emphasis> it matched the input. This is the part
that gives you back the structured information. For our word parser,
it’s pretty simple and obvious:</para>

<programlisting language="xml" linenumbering="unnumbered"><![CDATA[<sentence>
   <word>
      <consonant>c</consonant>
      <vowel>a</vowel>
      <consonant>t</consonant>
   </word>
</sentence>]]></programlisting>

<para>Broadly speaking, Invisible XML makes each nonterminal in your
grammar into an XML element. In fact, it offers you a number of ways to
control how the results are constructed, including which nonterminals
should be output, which things should be elements and which should be
attributes, and even which things to elide altogether. We’ll come back
to those topics when we talk about writing grammars in the next article.</para>

<para>There are two other things to bear in mind. First, the grammar only
validates against its rules. According to this grammar “xeq bei” is a
perfectly fine sentence. Second, an input may be ambiguous with respect
to a grammar. Consider the sentence “hey bee”. If you parse that with our
sentence grammar, you’ll get:</para>

<programlisting language="xml" linenumbering="unnumbered"><![CDATA[<sentence xmlns:ixml="http://invisiblexml.org/NS"
          ixml:state="ambiguous">
   <word>
      <consonant>h</consonant>
      <vowel>e</vowel>
      <vowel>y</vowel>
   </word>
   <word>
      <consonant>b</consonant>
      <vowel>e</vowel>
      <vowel>e</vowel>
   </word>
</sentence>]]></programlisting>

<para>Or maybe you’ll get:</para>

<programlisting language="xml" linenumbering="unnumbered"><![CDATA[<sentence xmlns:ixml="http://invisiblexml.org/NS"
          ixml:state="ambiguous">
   <word>
      <consonant>h</consonant>
      <vowel>e</vowel>
      <consonant>y</consonant>
   </word>
   <word>
      <consonant>b</consonant>
      <vowel>e</vowel>
      <vowel>e</vowel>
   </word>
</sentence>]]></programlisting>

<para>There are two different ways to parse the input because our
grammar says that a “y” can be either a consonant or a vowel. The word
“hey” therefore matches both the pattern “consonant-vowel-vowel” and the pattern
“consonant-vowel-consonant”.
That makes the results ambiguous. The Invisible XML processor is
required to tell us that, and it’s required to return one of the valid
parses. (Implementations may give you more control than that, but
that’s all that’s required for conformance.)</para>

<para>You might now be asking yourself, what about the word “gym”? Would that
be ambiguous too? It is, in some sense “ambiguous” because it’s either
“consonant-vowel-consonant” or
“consonant-consonant-consonant”.
But it’s not ambiguous in <emphasis>this grammar</emphasis> because
“consonant-consonant-consonant” isn’t a possible match.</para>

<para>Ambiguity is ok, and sometimes it’s necessary. The ambiguity in
this grammar is an inherent property of the English language rule that
“y” sometimes represents the sound of a vowel and sometimes it
represents the sound of a consonant.</para>

<para>That said, the more ambiguity there is, the more possibilities
the parser may have to consider when it’s looking for matches. That
can make the process slower. We’ll look more at ambiguity when we
start writing grammars in the next part.</para>

<para>Here, finally, is a grammar for the contacts format:</para>

<programlisting>contacts: (contact, NL*)+ .
contact: name, NL, (email, NL)?, (phone, NL)? .

name: letter, ~[#a; "@"]* .
email: username, "@", domainname .
phone: ["+0123456789()- "]+ .

-username: (letter; ["+-."])+ .
-domainname: (letter; ["+-."])+ .

-letter: [L] .
-NL: -#a ; -#d, -#a .</programlisting>

<para>It can be read like this:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>contacts</emphasis> file consists of
one or more contact items followed by
zero or more newlines.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>contact</emphasis> is a name followed by a newline,
optionally followed by an email followed by a newline, optionally followed
by a phone followed by a newline.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>name</emphasis> is a letter followed by any characters
except newline or “@”.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>An <emphasis>email</emphasis> is a username followed by “@”
followed by a domainname.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>phone</emphasis> is one or more digits or the
“+”, “(“, “)”, “-”, and space punctuation characters.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>username</emphasis> is one or more occurrences
of letter or any of the characters “+”, “-”, and “.”.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>domainname</emphasis> is one or more occurrences
of letter or any of the characters “+”, “-”, and “.”.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>letter</emphasis> is any character in the Unicode
character class “L” (letters).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <emphasis>NL</emphasis> is a newline or the sequence carriage return
followed by newline.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>If you give that grammar and the contacts file to an Invisible
XML processor, it will return:</para>

<programlisting linenumbering="unnumbered"><![CDATA[<contacts>
   <contact>
      <name>John Doe</name>
      <email>john@example.com</email>
      <phone>555-1234</phone>
   </contact>
   <contact>
      <name>Mary Smith</name>
      <email>m.smith@estaff.example.com</email>
      <phone>+1-222-555-2344</phone>
   </contact>
   <contact>
      <name>Jane Doe</name>
      <phone>(512) 555-9999</phone>
   </contact>
   <contact>
      <name>Nancy Jones</name>
      <email>nancy@example.org</email>
   </contact>
</contacts>]]></programlisting>

<para>Or the author of the processor might allow you to ask for the output in JSON
instead:</para>

<programlisting linenumbering="unnumbered">{
  "contacts": {
    "contact": [
      {
        "name": "John Doe",
        "email": "john@example.com",
        "phone": "555-1234"
      },
      {
        "name": "Mary Smith",
        "email": "m.smith@estaff.example.com",
        "phone": "+1-222-555-2344"
      },
      {
        "name": "Jane Doe",
        "phone": "(512) 555-9999"
      },
      {
        "name": "Nancy Jones",
        "email": "nancy@example.org"
      }
    ]
  }
}</programlisting>

<para>Or maybe in CSV:</para>

<programlisting linenumbering="unnumbered">"name","email","phone"
"John Doe","john@example.com","555-1234"
"Mary Smith","m.smith@estaff.example.com","+1-222-555-2344"
"Jane Doe",,"(512) 555-9999"
"Nancy Jones","nancy@example.org",</programlisting>

<para>Every Invisible XML processor begins by creating a basic XML
representation of your input data. That’s why it’s called Invisible
XML. But what’s really going on here is that we’re turning input with
implicit structure into explicitly structured data that can be
transformed into whatever output format we require. And we’re doing it
by describing that format in a compact, understandable, reusable,
testable way.</para>

<para>Join us next time for a detailed look at the syntax of Invisible
XML.</para>

</article>

